Joseph Keller used to jog around the Stanford campus,
اعتاد (جوزيف كيلر) أن يهرول حول حرم جامعة ستانفورد،
and he was struck by all the women jogging there as well.
و دُهش بسبب جميع النساء اللواتي يهرولن هناك أيضًا.
Why did their ponytails swing from side to side like that?
لماذا يتمايل شعرهن من جانب لأخر هكذا؟
Being a mathematician, he set out to understand why.
بصفته متخصصًا بالرياضيات، أراد أن يفهم السبب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Professor Keller was curious about many things:
شعر البروفيسور (كيلر) بالفضول حيال أشياء كثيرة:
why teapots dribble
لمَ تُقطِر أباريق الشاي
or how earthworms wriggle.
أو كيف تتلوى ديدان الأرض.
Until a few months ago, I hadn't heard of Joseph Keller.
حتى أشهر قليلة مضت، لم أسمع عن (جوزيف كيلر).
I read about him in the New York Times,
قرأت عنه في صحيفة نيويورك تايمز،
in the obituaries.
في صفحة النعي.
The Times had half a page of editorial dedicated to him,
خصصت التايمز له نصف صفحة من الافتتاحية،
which you can imagine is premium space for a newspaper of their stature.
ويمكنك أن تتخيل أنها مساحة مميزة لجريدة في قامتها.
I read the obituaries almost every day.
أقرأ صفحة النعي كل يوم تقريبًا.
My wife understandably thinks I'm rather morbid
تعتقد زوجتي بشكل مفهوم أني مصاب بحالة مَرَضية
to begin my day with scrambled eggs and a "Let's see who died today."
لبداية يومي بتناول بيض مقليّ و "لنر من توفي اليوم."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But if you think about it,
لكن إذا أمعنتم النظر،
the front page of the newspaper is usually bad news,
ستجدون أن الصفحة الأولى من الجريدة عادةً ما تحتوي على أخبار سيئة،
and cues man's failures.
وتشير إلى إخفاقات الناس.
An instance where bad news cues accomplishment
مثال على أن الأخبار السيئة تشير إلى الإنجازات
is at the end of the paper, in the obituaries.
هو في نهاية الصحيفة، في قسم النعي.
In my day job,
في عملي اليومي،
I run a company that focuses on future insights
أدير شركة تركز على تكوين رؤى مستقبلية
that marketers can derive from past data --
والتي يستطيع المسوِّقون أن يستنبطوها من البيانات القديمة --
a kind of rearview-mirror analysis.
كنوع من التحليل الاسترجاعي.
And we began to think:
وبدأنا التفكير:
What if we held a rearview mirror to obituaries from the New York Times?
ماذا لو أعدنا رؤية ماضي الوفيات من صحيفة نيويورك تايمز؟
Were there lessons on how you could get your obituary featured --
هل كانت هناك دروس عن كيفية الحصول على شكل نعْيِك--
even if you aren't around to enjoy it?
حتى لو لم تكن موجودًا ليعجبك؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Would this go better with scrambled eggs?
هل سيكون هذا أفضل مع البيض المقليّ؟
And so, we looked at the data.
وبالتالي، فحصنا البيانات.
2,000 editorial, non-paid obituaries
2,000 نعي افتتاحي وغير مدفوع
over a 20-month period between 2015 and 2016.
خلال فترة تزيد عن عشرين شهرًا بين عامي 2015 و 2016.
What did these 2,000 deaths -- rather, lives -- teach us?
ماذا علمتنا هذه الوفيات الألفين أو بالأحرى هذه الحيوات؟
Well, first we looked at words.
حسنًا، أولًا تمعنَّا في الكلمات.
This here is an obituary headline.
هذا هنا نعْي في عنوان رئيسي.
This one is of the amazing Lee Kuan Yew.
هذا الآخر للرائع (لي كوان يو).
If you remove the beginning and the end,
إذا مسحت البداية والنهاية،
you're left with a beautifully worded descriptor
سيتبقى لديك مُصِيغ للكلمات بشكل جمالي
that tries to, in just a few words, capture an achievement or a lifetime.
الذي يحاول، في كلمات قليلة، أن يلخص إنجازعظيم أو حياة كاملة.
Just looking at these is fascinating.
مجرد النظر لهذه الكلمات هو شيء مدهش.
Here are a few famous ones, people who died in the last two years.
إليكم هذه الكلمات عن مشاهير ممن توفوا في العامين الأخيرين.
Try and guess who they are.
حاولوا تخمين من يكونوا.
[An Artist who Defied Genre]
(فنان قام بتعريف الفن)
That's Prince.
إنه (برنس).
[Titan of Boxing and the 20th Century]
(عملاق الملاكمة والقرن العشرين)
Oh, yes.
نعم، صحيح.
[Muhammad Ali]
(محمد علي)
[Groundbreaking Architect]
(مهندسة معماريّة مبدعة)
Zaha Hadid.
(زاها حديد).
So we took these descriptors
لذا نأخذ هذه التوصيفات
and did what's called natural language processing,
ونقوم بعمل ما يطلق عليه معالجة اللغة الطبيعية،
where you feed these into a program,
حيث تضع هذه الكلمات في برنامج،
it throws out the superfluous words --
ليحذف الكلمات الزائدة --
"the," "and," -- the kind of words you can mime easily in "Charades," --
مثل "ال، و" -- الكلمات التي تتمكن من محاكاتها بسهولة في "الألغاز" --
and leaves you with the most significant words.
ويُبْقِي على الكلمات الأكثر أهمية.
And we did it not just for these four,
ولم نفعلها لأجل هؤلاء الأربعة فقط،
but for all 2,000 descriptors.
لكن في جميع توصيفات الألفَين.
And this is what it looks like.
وهذا ما يبدو عليه.
Film, theatre, music, dance and of course, art, are huge.
إن الأفلام والمسرح والموسيقى والرقص وبالطبع الفن نسبتها كبيرة.
Over 40 percent.
أكثر من 40 بالمئة.
You have to wonder why in so many societies
عليك أن تتساءل لماذا في كثير من المجتمعات
we insist that our kids pursue engineering or medicine or business or law
نصرّ على أولادنا أن يسعوا وراء الهندسة أو الطب أو الأعمال أو الحقوق
to be construed as successful.
ليُنظر إليهم كأشخاص ناجحين.
And while we're talking profession,
و عندما نتحدث عن المهن،
let's look at age --
دعونا نهتم بالعمر --
the average age at which they achieved things.
متوسط العمر الذي يحققون به إنجاز.
That number is 37.
هذا العدد هو 37.
What that means is, you've got to wait 37 years ...
ذلك يعني أن عليك الانتظار 37 عاما ...
before your first significant achievement that you're remembered for --
قبل تحقيق أول إنجاز مهم لك ليتذكرك الناس به --
on average --
في المتوسط --
44 years later, when you die at the age of 81 --
بعد 44 عاما، عندما تموت عن عمر 81 --
on average.
في المتوسط.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Talk about having to be patient.
عليك أن تكون صبورًا.
Of course, it varies by profession.
بالطبع، تختلف حسب المهنة.
If you're a sports star,
إذا كنت نجمًا رياضيًا،
you'll probably hit your stride in your 20s.
ستحقق نجاحًا كبيرًا في العشرينات من عمرك.
And if you're in your 40s like me,
وإذا كنت في الأربعينات مثلي،
you can join the fun world of politics.
تستطيع الانضمام إلى عالم السياسة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Politicians do their first and sometimes only commendable act in their mid-40s.
يقوم السياسون بأولى أعمالهم المحمودة وأحيانًا الوحيدة في منتصف الأربعينات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If you're wondering what "others" are,
إذا كنت تتساءل عن أعمال "الآخرين"،
here are some examples.
إليك بعض الأمثلة.
Isn't it fascinating, the things people do
إنها مذهلة، الأشياء التي يقوم بها البعض
and the things they're remembered for?
والأشياء التي يتذكرهم الناس بها؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Our curiosity was in overdrive,
ازداد فضولنا أكثر،
and we desired to analyze more than just a descriptor.
وأردنا ان نحلل أكثر من مجرد توصيف.
So, we ingested the entire first paragraph of all 2,000 obituaries,
لذا استوعبنا الفقرة الأولى بالكامل من الألفي نعي،
but we did this separately for two groups of people:
لكننا قمنا بهذا كلٌ على حدة لمجموعتين من الناس:
people that are famous and people that are not famous.
الأشخاص المشهورين وغير المشهورين.
Famous people -- Prince, Ali, Zaha Hadid --
المشهورين أمثال (برنس)-- و(علي) و (زاها حديد) --
people who are not famous are people like Jocelyn Cooper,
وأشخاص غير مشهورين مثل (جوسلين كوبر)،
Reverend Curry
أو (القس كاري)
or Lorna Kelly.
أو (لورنا كيلي).
I'm willing to bet you haven't heard of most of their names.
أراهن أنكم لم تسمعوا عن أغلب أسمائهم.
Amazing people, fantastic achievements, but they're not famous.
أناس رائعين وحققوا إنجازات مذهلة و مع ذلك ليسوا مشهورين.
So what if we analyze these two groups separately --
لذا ماذا لو قمنا بتحليل هاتين المجموعتين كل على حدى --
the famous and the non-famous?
المشهورين وغير المشهورين؟
What might that tell us?
ماذا قد يخبرنا هذا؟
Take a look.
ألقوا نظرة.
Two things leap out at me.
لفت نظري شيئان.
First:
الأول:
"John."
"جون."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Anyone here named John should thank your parents --
أي شخص هنا يسمى (جون) عليه أن يشكر أبويه --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
and remind your kids to cut out your obituary when you're gone.
وذكّروا أبناءكم أن يقصُّوا نعْيَكم عند وفاتكم.
And second:
والثاني:
"help."
"المساعدة."
We uncovered, many lessons from lives well-led,
نحن نكشف العديد من الدروس المستفادة من حياة ناس تركوا بصمة،
and what those people immortalized in print could teach us.
و ما تعلمنا من هؤلاء الأفراد المخلَّدين في الصحف.
The exercise was a fascinating testament to the kaleidoscope that is life,
كانت هذه العملية دليل مذهل على متغيرات الحياة،
and even more fascinating
والأكثر دهشة من ذلك
was the fact that the overwhelming majority of obituaries
حقيقة أن الغالبية العظمى من النعايا
featured people famous and non-famous,
تبرز المشهورين وغير المشهورين،
who did seemingly extraordinary things.
الذين قاموا بأشياء مذهلة على ما يبدو.
They made a positive dent in the fabric of life.
تركوا طابع إيجابي في نسيج الحياة.
They helped.
قاموا بالمساعدة.
So ask yourselves as you go back to your daily lives:
لذا اسائِلوا أنفسكم في حياتكم اليومية:
How am I using my talents to help society?
كيف أستخدم مواهبي لمساعدة المجتمع؟
Because the most powerful lesson here is,
لأن أكثر عِبرة مؤثرة هنا،
if more people lived their lives trying to be famous in death,
إذا عاش المزيد من الناس حياتهم محاولين أن يكونوا مشهورين عند موتهم،
the world would be a much better place.
فإن العالم سيكون مكانًا أفضل بكثير.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)